<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Becoming a Maker</title><description>Thoughts, stories and ideas.</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.6</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 13:29:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>What is Red-Green-Refactor and how does it relate to TDD?</title><description>&lt;p&gt;So what is &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color="red"&gt;Red&lt;/font&gt;-&lt;font color="green"&gt;Green&lt;/font&gt;-&lt;font color="black"&gt;Refactor&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; I hear you asking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red-Green-Refactor is one of many methods for conducting TDD (test driven development). The steps are red, green and refactor. These are defined below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color="black"&gt;Think&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - Break down your problem into smaller parts so that a test can be&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/what-is-red-green-refactor-and-how-does-it-relate-to-tdd/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">bafd3153-97ec-4e60-8f89-70499d2c7bfe</guid><dc:creator>Usman Jamil</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 10:10:54 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;So what is &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color="red"&gt;Red&lt;/font&gt;-&lt;font color="green"&gt;Green&lt;/font&gt;-&lt;font color="black"&gt;Refactor&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; I hear you asking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red-Green-Refactor is one of many methods for conducting TDD (test driven development). The steps are red, green and refactor. These are defined below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color="black"&gt;Think&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - Break down your problem into smaller parts so that a test can be written for each part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color="red"&gt;Red&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - Write the test for your first problem. This should be short and concise. The test should fail as you will not have any code written for it to pass at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color="green"&gt;Green&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - Write some code, just enough; so that the test that you just wrote passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color="black"&gt;Refactor&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - Now that your test has passed, go back and refactor your code to make it clearer and more readable. Try to get rid of any duplications and excess code. Run the test again to ensure it still passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color="black"&gt;Repeat&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - This can be repeated a number of times until you are satisfied that your code is readable, passing the tests and concise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first working  version of any code can always be improved - even if its not messy. Therefore you would use Red-Green-Refactor to improve the code, make it cleaner, make it more readable and also remove any duplications. Using this method allows you to refactor safely without breaking any code as you are constantly testing the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usman &amp;amp; Dom&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Pre-Course Week 4</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;WOW. Pre-course is over!!&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've learnt a lot during this month. However the last week was hectic. Had to make the most of the last week before becoming a FULL-TIME MAKER! So I went away for three days to Manchester &amp;amp; Sheffield with the family; to meet family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn't&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/pre-course-week-4/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b031c565-28b0-4a43-afdc-8a0de53c167a</guid><dc:creator>Usman Jamil</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2015 21:40:38 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;WOW. Pre-course is over!!&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've learnt a lot during this month. However the last week was hectic. Had to make the most of the last week before becoming a FULL-TIME MAKER! So I went away for three days to Manchester &amp;amp; Sheffield with the family; to meet family. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn't forget Ruby whilst I was away though. I started on 'The Well-Grounded Rubyist' by David A. Black. I've got to chapter 5. It's a pretty good read and has many activities to do whilst reading it (doesn't let you get lazy). I also continued with Codewars. I set myself a target of reaching 125 honour. I didn't reach that target. I did however get up to 104. Main reason being that I was away and I was also doing exercises from the textbook. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack's been quiet over the weekend (Messenger that Makers use). I'm assuming everyones relaxing a little before we start in full force tomorrow. Well I'm off too; need to catch a good nights sleep tonight ready for our first full day. Very excited! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll update you guys on more during the week :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usman&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Pre-Course Week 3</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;It's been a crazy week! Chris Pine tried to take over my life. But I dumped him for Ruby Kickstart.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were told at the pre-course launch, after week 2 things were going to get real hard. And they were. Ruby literally took over my life. The torture of&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/pre-course-week-3/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">02694639-5a7e-4b5b-a6ae-4388dc14ce4f</guid><dc:creator>Usman Jamil</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2015 21:45:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;It's been a crazy week! Chris Pine tried to take over my life. But I dumped him for Ruby Kickstart.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were told at the pre-course launch, after week 2 things were going to get real hard. And they were. Ruby literally took over my life. The torture of being so close to solving a challenge yet being so far. My head started to hurt by the end of the week. But theres no giving up! In fact it feels like a game, its so addictive. You don't even feel like your working/studying. It's just so fun. My peers are all so much fun too. The environment is so cool! I'm loving it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway so I managed to complete Ruby Kickstarter (going to try and complete Chris Pine this week) and I've managed to get &lt;b&gt;70&lt;/b&gt; points on codewars. I'm going to try and get 125 by the end of the week (fingers crossed). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've had a long week so I'm going to hit the bed. Need to be up early tomorrow for some more Ruby! See what I mean, its addictive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adios for now. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usman&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Pair Programming and Graduation Day!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Graduation day for the seniors! An exciting day for all of Makers. So we thought we'd make use of this day; we decided to meet up earlier and crack on with some pair programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met up for 2.30pm and got into our pairs. We used a ruby built&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/pair-programming-and-graduation-day/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">2218aaca-d81f-4000-b59d-42c1b35c3788</guid><dc:creator>Usman Jamil</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2015 21:32:13 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Graduation day for the seniors! An exciting day for all of Makers. So we thought we'd make use of this day; we decided to meet up earlier and crack on with some pair programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met up for 2.30pm and got into our pairs. We used a ruby built software to randomly put us in our pairs. You can find the code for this in my repos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair programming was a fun exercie which was extremely beneficial. I felt that I learnt a lot during this exercise. I learnt of new ways to go about solving a situation and also found out about various tools which make it easier to solve problems. This was a team work exercise which allowed me to learn from my peer and also share my knowledge which they may not have. After a few hours of pair programming, it was time for graduation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graduation consisted of 6 presentations which all lasted roughly 5 minutes each. The presentations were amazing. The platforms that each team had built with only 12 weeks of coding were really a true representation of how much one can learn in such a short time. The teams all used various technologies in their projects and were not restricted to just Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the graduation we all socialised for a good 2 hours. Everyone was so friendly. It felt as if I knew everyone since ages. A bunch of cool people all under one roof! Before joining Makers I didn't know what to expect; but I'm honestly so happy to be a part of this hard working team. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone went out after but I had to attend a family dinner so couldn't go along with everyone; otherwise I definitely would have! Theres always next time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that was graduation day. A great experience. Hopefully many more great experiences to come. Keep an eye out on my blog and follow my journey at Makers Academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usman&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Pre-Course Week 2</title><description>&lt;p&gt;This weeks task involved getting use to version control (git). I had used git previously on one occasion, but I ended up deleting everything from the git and loosing all my work. This time round I managed to keep all my work safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were advised to go over the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/pre-course-week-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">96781a78-a13c-4dc5-8fb2-d9a05a9a4958</guid><dc:creator>Usman Jamil</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 14:08:13 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This weeks task involved getting use to version control (git). I had used git previously on one occasion, but I ended up deleting everything from the git and loosing all my work. This time round I managed to keep all my work safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were advised to go over the exercises on &lt;a href="http://gitimmersion.com"&gt;Git Immersion&lt;/a&gt;. This was very hands on and increased my understanding of git immensely. However I did struggle to understand the variation between merging and rebasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I also deployed my Ghost blog on GitHub. This was made easy due to my understanding of Git and GitHub. Having spoken to some of my peers on Slack, I gathered that many people were struggling to deploy their blogs onto GitHub. Due to this I created a 'How to' blog on how to create a Ghost blog locally and then deploy it onto GitHub. This can be found &lt;a href="http://usmanj.github.io/setting-up-a-ghost-blog-on-github/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the experience has been very hands on and I have learnt a lot about using git/GitHub. I have also developed further my command line skills from the previous week by using command line constantly during the course of the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to finish all the version control work early and was pretty confident with it so I went on and started going over &lt;a href="https://pine.fm/LearnToProgram/chap_00.html"&gt;Chris Pine's exercises&lt;/a&gt;. I had done this prior to my Maker's interview but decided to go over it again to jog my memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's it for this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow my blog for more updates during the next week and many more weeks to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usman&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Setting up a Ghost blog on GitHub</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having struggled to host my blog on GitHub I thought I'd write up a blog post about it to help everyone who may be struggling with it too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Installing Node.js&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, we need to install Node.js because Ghost is written in Node.js.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this,&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/setting-up-a-ghost-blog-on-github/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8c225039-3673-4011-a3b4-6bbbd80767b5</guid><dc:creator>Usman Jamil</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 12:14:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having struggled to host my blog on GitHub I thought I'd write up a blog post about it to help everyone who may be struggling with it too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Installing Node.js&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, we need to install Node.js because Ghost is written in Node.js.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, open your terminal and enter the following command:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install node&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;This should install Node.js&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also install Node.js by downloading the appropriate installation file from &lt;a href="https://nodejs.org/download/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Installing Buster&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to install Buster which is a tool that will allow you to export your Ghost blog pages into static pages; which you can then deploy to your blog on GitHub. To install Buster we will also need to install Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install Buster, enter the following commands in your terminal:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install python&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install wget&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip install buster&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should install Buster for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Setting up Ghost locally&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to set up Ghost locally. To do this you will need to download Ghost from their website (&lt;a href="https://www.ghost.org"&gt;https://www.ghost.org&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have downloaded ghost and exported it into the directory that you want to keep it in, you will need to set it up locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start off by opening another terminal window and going to your ghost directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install npm using the following command. npm is a manager for installing Node.js applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have installed npm, we need to start it in order to run Ghost locally. We do this by using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm start&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Ghost will be running locally on your machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to the following link in order to create a Ghost account locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://127.0.0.1:2368/ghost"&gt;http://127.0.0.1:2368/ghost&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create a GitHub repository&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Once you have created your account, you will now need to create a new repository on GitHub which will be connected to your ghost blog. Leave ghost to run locally in the background and just minimise that shell for now as we will not be needing it (but will need it to carry on running locally in the background for when we want to deploy the blog to GitHub).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to your GitHub account and create a repository called "username.github.io". Change username to your own username. For example in my  case the repository is called "usmanj.github.io". &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create a directory for your static pages&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Now go back to your first terminal shell (which should be in the ghost directory) and create a new folder. Call it the same name as your repository (username.github.io). You do not have to do this, but I did this because it will allow you to keep your static pages separate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Setup Buster&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have made another directory for the static pages, you can setup Buster in that folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;buster setup https://github.com/username/username.github.io.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this is done, run the following command which will generate all the needed files under the static subfolder created in the previous step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;buster generate --domain=http://127.0.0.1:2368&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Push static folder to GitHub&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Now enter that directory in your terminal by using &lt;code&gt;cd static&lt;/code&gt; and then add all the files in that static folder to your git. Initialise your git by &lt;code&gt;git init&lt;/code&gt; followed by adding all files to the git by running &lt;code&gt;git add --all&lt;/code&gt;. Once this is done, commit the changes using &lt;code&gt;git commit -m "Initial commit"&lt;/code&gt; and finally push it all to your GitHub repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To push to your repository you will need to add the remote using the following commands (replace username with your own username):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;git remote add origin https://github.com/username/username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;git push -u origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HURRRAAAYYY!!! Your blog should now be online on &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it isn't, drop me a message on Slack and I will try to help you get it up and running. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Deploying changes to GitHub&lt;/h3&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, how will we deploy any changes to the local blog? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have added/edited/deleted blog posts from your local ghost blog, you will need to deploy the changes to GitHub. To do this, go to your username.github.io folder directory in terminal (do not go into static).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once your are in there and your local ghost is running in another shell; run the following commands:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;buster generate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;buster deploy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this helps you guys if you were stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usman&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Pre-Course Week 1</title><description>&lt;p&gt;So week 1 flew by. Our pre-course week 1 was based on command-line. I had not ever studied command-line prior to this. I studied the online material which was posted on the pre-course website followed by trying out the practise exercises. I was surprised by how quickly I picked things&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/pre-course-week-1/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c39e942-b8a8-400a-93d3-288db7f01597</guid><dc:creator>Usman Jamil</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 12:15:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;So week 1 flew by. Our pre-course week 1 was based on command-line. I had not ever studied command-line prior to this. I studied the online material which was posted on the pre-course website followed by trying out the practise exercises. I was surprised by how quickly I picked things up. The few things that I struggled with were solved quickly by the support of my peers via the slack app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began on the weekly test on the Friday and it didn't take too long to complete (but took longer than the 1 hours target stated in the test description). The instructions were really straight forward and some material required you to conduct your own research (google). I learnt a lot from this exercise and I'm sure next week I will learn even more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I did not use the git issues page which I will try to make use of next week. However I have been using Slack to communicate with my peers which has proved to be very beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's it for this week as it wasn't too full on, pretty straight forward. However I'm sure it will get harder and harder as the course goes on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to the next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usman&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Makers Academy Pre-Course Launch Evening</title><description>&lt;p&gt;August 3rd was the day I first went in to meet my fellow students at Makers. As I got to the building straight away I met a new student like myself. By the time I was upstairs I had met 3 new people who were ambitious and pumped up ready&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/makers-academy-pre-course-launch-evening/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5331104d-c8ff-47d0-9a84-839db3adbe3d</guid><dc:creator>Usman Jamil</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 17:35:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;August 3rd was the day I first went in to meet my fellow students at Makers. As I got to the building straight away I met a new student like myself. By the time I was upstairs I had met 3 new people who were ambitious and pumped up ready to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch was short but sweet. All the students of the September cohort introduced themselves. Students were from a wide variety of backgrounds; lawyers to a student fresh out of high school. Nikesh continued the evening by introducing us to GitHub, Slack and the Pre-course material. At the end of the short launch; some students went off to the local bar down the road and others headed home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The excitement has been building for my Makers journey and I hope to share all my experiences with you guys. I hope to learn a lot from this experience and am very determined to make the most of it. Follow my blog to get regular updates on my progress and my makers experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck to all my peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usman&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>